A Guide to the Records of the Office of the Associate Provost, Patricia Hyer, 1937-2013
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech
Records of the Office of the Associate Provost, Patricia Hyer, 1937-2013
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
RG 5/1/10a
2.2 Cubic Feet; 3 boxes
This collection contains materials from Patricia Hyer's tenure as Associate Provost at Virginia Tech, covering such subjects as inclusion and diversity, women's issues, the AdvanceVT program, and strategic planning. The collection also includes some biographical information.
Hyer, Patricia B. (Patricia Brown), 1948-
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Source of Acquisition
This collection was transferred to Special Collections and University Archives in 2011. Additional materials were donated in 2014 and 2015.
Biographical Note
Dr. Patricia Brown "Pat" Hyer served two decades as Associate Provost at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University under six Provosts, including E. Fred Carlisle, Peggy S. Meszaros, and Mark G. McNamee. Before taking this position, she earned her bachelor's degree from Hillsdale College in Michigan, two master's degrees at the University of Michigan, and finally a Ph.D. in educational policy studies from Virginia Tech. She also worked in administrative roles at Old Dominion University, University of Maryland, and Virginia Tech.
Some of Hyer's accomplishments as Associate Provost include establishing the Women's Center at Virginia Tech and setting up wide-ranging and effective diversity policies for the University. She has also been influential as a member of the Virginia Network, a statewide organization for women in higher education in Virginia, serving as state coordinator for three years and then on its board of directors for fifteen years.
Hyer has received numerous awards for her service, including Woman of the Year, Leader of the Year, and Woman of the Decade. She retired in 2010.
Scope and Content
The Records of the Office of the Associate Provost, Patricia Hyer, 1937-2013, contains materials from her tenure as Associate Provost at Virginia Tech, covering such subjects as inclusion and diversity, women's issues, the AdvanceVT program, and strategic planning. The collection also includes some biographical information and photographs.
Series I: Biographical Materials and Photographs, 2004, 2011, n.d., includes a biography and curriculum vitae of Patricia Hyer as well as photographs of the Women's Center staff and a calendar cover from 2004.
Series II: Strategic Planning at Virginia Tech, 1972-2009, contains primarily printed materials, such as institutional research reports, information on graduation and non-returning student rates, historical information on the university, and materials from a Board of Visitors 2008 Strategic Planning Retreat. This series also includes information on the 1994 College of Education restructuring.
Series III: History of Women and Women's Issues, 1937-2010, consists of historical research, newspaper articles, speeches/presentations and reports. There are interviews with early women students and faculty, results from surveys about equality, general information on women in academia, materials on the foundation and history of the Women's Center on campus, and progress reports.
Series IV: AdvanceVT, 2002-2010, consists primarily of AdvanceVT annual reports from 2004 through 2009, along with the original NSF proposal. Additional materials are from the 2004 AdvanceVT Advisory Committee meeting, flyers and other ephemera from AdvanceVT events, and an incomplete set of AdvanceVT newsletters from 2004 through 2010.
Series V: Diversity Issues, 1990-2013, contains reports and research on diversity, multicultural affairs, affirmative action issues, and strategic planning for diversity. There are also reports on undergraduate African American enrollment, results from a 1999 campus climate survey, and documents from "Growing and Sustaining a Diverse and Inclusive Environment: 2010-2013 VT Diversity Strategic Plan."
Arrangement
The collection is divided into five series. Within each series, materials are in chronological order.
Series I: Biographical Materials and Photographs, 2004, 2011, n.d.
Series II: Strategic Planning at Virginia Tech, 1972-2009
Series III: History of Women and Women's Issues, 1937-2010
Series IV: AdvanceVT, 2002-2010
Series V: Diversity Issues, 1990-2013
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Archival Material
Two additional speeches by Laura Jane Harper are available online from Special Collections and University Archives.
Rights Statement for Archival Description
The guide to the Records of the Office of the Associate Provost, Patricia Hyer by Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech, is licensed under a CC0 (https://creativecommons.org/share-your- work/public-domain/cc0/).
Index Terms
Subjects:
Inclusion and diversity in higher education; University Archives; University History; Women -- History; Women in higher education
Organizations:
Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. Office of the Provost
People:
Hyer, Patricia B. (Patricia Brown), 1948-
Contents List
- Series I: Biographical Materials and Photographs, 2004, 2011, n.d.
  - Brief Biography, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, 2004, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Series II: Strategic Planning at Virginia Tech, 1972-2008
  - Reports Removed to Catalogue, 1972-2004 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Report on Graduation Rates, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Institutional Research Reports, 1991-2000 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Bibliography
    Research Reports Bibliography
    Testing Significance of Tenure and Promotion, 1991
    Testing Significance of Tenure and Promotion as Related to Gender, 1995
    University Faculty and Staff 1986 to 1996, 1996
    Instructional Faculty Demographics, 1997
    A Statistical Evaluation of the Effectiveness of the Math Emporium, 1999
    Instructional Faculty Demographics, 1999
    Trends in Student Retention and Graduation Rates, 2000
  - VT Academic Administration Fact Book Fall 1992, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - A Decade of Admissions Data, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Preliminary Plan for Restructuring of the College of Education, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Non-Returning Student Analysis, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Leadership Meeting on Faculty Worklife Issues, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Board of Visitors Strategic Planning Retreat, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - VT Climate Survey Results, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
- Series III: History of Women and Women's Issues, 1962-2010
  - Presentations and Articles on Women and Women's History at VT, 1937-1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Presentations and Articles on Women and Women's History at VT, 1995-2006 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Presentations and Articles on Women and Women's History at VT, 2010-2011, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Harper's "Education of Women at VPI", 1962 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Lancaster Interview, "How Times Have Changed", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Fabric of Women in Administration, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Perceptions of Sex Equality, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Status of Women at VPI&SU: 5-year Progress Report, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Child Care Studies, 1983-1984, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Female Faculty at VT Study, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Women Faculty at VT: Analysis by Disc and Rank Institutional Research, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Chronology and Summary of Studies on Women at Virginia Tech, 1981-1982 to 1990-1991, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Organization of Women Faculty, 1993-2001 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Women's Center Original Proposal, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - History of Women Students at VT, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Family Friendly Policies Task Force, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Women's History at VT Multimedia, ca. 2000s (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Women's Center Celebrating Sixteen Sweet Years Tribute to Pat Hyer" (2 copies, CD)
    - "Whammos, Whizbangs, & Whetstones: Women at Virginia Tech" powerpoint presentation by Clara Cox (CD)
    - Flash drive with "Creating the Future for Women at Virginia Tech" (2004) and "The Legacy: Women at Virginia Tech" powerpoint presentations
  - Resolution on the University's Policy Against Discrimination, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "Women at Virginia Tech" Presentation by Clara Cox, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "Cool Women of Virginia Tech" Calendar, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "Women at VT: Milestones on the Journey" Talk by Patricia Hyer, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Women's Center 16th Anniversary Tribute to Patricia Hyer, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - General Information on Women in Academia (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - General Information on Women at VT (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - "Legacies of Resistance and Survival: The First Black Women Students at Virginia Tech" (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Series IV: Advance VT, 2002-2009
  - Advance VT Original NSF Proposal, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - AdvanceVT Advisory Committee Meeting, 2004-01-22 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Advance VT Materials, 2004-2009 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - AdvanceVT Newsletters (incomplete run), 2004-2010 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - AdvanceVT Reports, Presentations, and Flyers, 2004-2009, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - AdvanceVT Annual Report, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - AdvanceVT Annual Report, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - AdvanceVT Annual Report, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - AdvanceVT Annual Report, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - AdvanceVT Annual Report, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - AdvanceVT Annual Report, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Series V: Diversity Issues, 1990-2005
  - Miscellaneous Diversity Documents, 1990-2005 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Robinson Dissertation Regarding Tenure for African American Faculty at VT, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Torgerson Address on Diversity, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - University-Wide Diversity Related Initiatives, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - "Women and Minorities at Virginia Tech", 1998 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - The Campus Climate for Diversity: Faculty Perceptions, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Multicultural Academic Opportunities Program (MAOP), 1999 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Diversity Report to SCHEV, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Report of the Provost's Task Force on Undergraduate Enrollment of African American Students, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Board of Visitors Denial of Shelli Fowler Appointment Materials, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Black Alumni Reunion, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Forum on Narrow Tailoring, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Narrow Tailoring / OCR Complaint, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - "Growing and Sustaining a Diverse and Inclusive Environment: 2010-2013 VT Diversity Strategic Plan" (Box 3, Folder 8-10)
  - Commitment to Affirmative Action (Box 1, Folder 45)